Hi, this is Matt Baker. Today I want to
talk to you about the word Israel,
because when I say Israel, I could be
talking about at least three different
things. First, I could be talking about
the modern state of Israel, established
in 1948. Or I could be talking about
ancient Israel, which is both mentioned
in the Bible as well as in the
archaeological record. Or I could be
talking about the Israel which in some
contexts is a word used to refer to the
entirety of the Jewish people. Now, the
reason I want to do this is because some
people mistakenly conflate these three
Israels together and assume that they
are all basically one and the same
thing. Now, obviously there are some
connections between these three Israels,
but there are also a lot of important
differences. And I think it's important
to understand these differences,
especially considering the global
situation we find ourselves in today.
So, let's start with ancient Israel,
which a lot of people misunderstand
because they either believe the biblical
account to be 100% true, or they believe
the biblical account to be 100% false.
In reality, ancient Israel did in fact
exist, meaning that it's not just some
myth that was created out of thin air,
but on the other hand, it did not exist
in quite the same way that it is
described in the Bible. In order to
explain, let me bring up our biblical
family tree chart, which by the way, you
can purchase as a poster from our
website usefulcharts.com.
Basically, the Bible presents a seamless
story starting with Adam and Eve, but
then quickly arriving at Abraham, who is
promised by God a land for his
descendants. A land that pretty much
corresponds to where modern Israel and
Palestine are located today. Abraham has
a son named Isaac, who in turn has a son
named Jacob, whose name is later changed
to Israel. Jacob, or Israel, has 12
sons, whose descendants, known as
Israelites, end up as slaves in Egypt,
where they are later rescued by Moses,
who brings them back to the promised
land, where they eventually set up a
kingdom called Israel, named after their
ancestor Jacob. This United Kingdom is
initially made up of all 12 tribes, each
one named after one of Jacob's 12 sons,
but eventually the kingdom splits into
two separate kingdoms, one in the north
called Israel because it consisted of
most of the tribes, and one in the south
called Judah because it consisted mostly
of just one tribe, the tribe of Judah.
Israel eventually gets conquered by
Assyria, and then about 100 years later
Judah gets conquered by Babylon. Okay,
let's stop there and zoom out. If we
match the biblical account with the
archaeological record, we learn that
basically everything up to Moses
occurred during the Bronze Age, whereas
everything involving the kingdoms of
Israel and Judah occurred during the
Iron Age. Now, can anything described in
the Bible actually be corroborated using
secular sources? Well, yes, some of it
can. For example, the Bible mentions a
king of ancient Israel named Omri, and a
stone slab called the Mesha Stele, dated
to around 840 BCE, also mentions a king
of Israel named Omri. And this is not
just a coincidence. The context is
exactly the same. So, basically all
secular historians agree that the Bible
and the Mesha Stele are referencing the
same person. Likewise, the Bible also
mentions a king of Judah named Hezekiah,
who was attacked by the Assyrians. Well,
according to contemporary Assyrian
records, the Assyrians did in fact
attack a king named Hezekiah at that
exact same time. Now, here's the
interesting thing. If we zoom back out
and give a checkmark to every person in
the Hebrew Bible whose name has been
found in the archaeological record in
the right context, what do you notice?
Well, they're all from the Iron Age.
This actually makes a lot of sense
because textual analysis of the Hebrew
Bible indicates that the vast majority
of it was written during the Iron Age. A
few books were written even later, but
no section of the Bible was written in
the Bronze Age. So, if we want to draw
conclusions about the biblical account
using the same rules that we use to
analyze other ancient texts, the
conclusion would be when it comes to the
Iron Age parts of the Bible, the events
described can pretty much be taken as
accurate, so long as we airbrush out a
few embellishments and theological
interpretations here and there.
Something we also have to do with say
the writings of Herodotus. However, when
it comes to the Bronze Age parts of the
Bible, what we're dealing with there is
almost certainly myth and legend. There
may be a grain or two of historical
memory in there, but basically we should
treat those parts the same way that we
would treat say Greek or Norse
mythology. So, from a purely historical
point of view, there was no man named
Abraham who was promised by God a
certain plot of land. And there was no
man named Jacob with 12 sons who had his
name changed to Israel. But, there
definitely was an ancient kingdom named
Israel whose people came up with certain
stories in order to explain their
origins. And there also definitely was
an ancient kingdom named Judah that was
somehow related to ancient Israel. By
the way, if you want to know the secular
explanation for where these two kingdoms
came from, if not from Jacob, I
previously did a video on that exact
topic, which I'll link to in the
description. But, before I talk about
the second meaning of the word Israel, I
want to shout out today's sponsor,
Ground News, which is the website and
app that I use to keep up with events
happening around the world. What makes
Ground News different is that it pulls
headlines from multiple sources,
including newspapers, podcasts, and
websites. It then categorizes them on a
continuum from left to right, so that
you get to look at the same news story
from multiple angles. Something that is
particularly important when it comes to
events happening in, say, the Middle
East. For example, when a recent story
broke about the detained Palestinian
doctor, Hassam Abu Safieh, left-wing
sources focused on the imminent danger
to his life and quoted him as saying
that Israel needs to kill him. Whereas
right-wing sources were much softer,
focusing on his medical condition in
plainer terms. Ground News also has a
blind spot feed, which highlights
stories that one side of the spectrum is
barely covering at all. For example,
very few right-wing sources covered this
story about 13 new settlements in the
West Bank. Whereas very few left-wing
sources covered this story. As you can
see by checking the blind spot feed, you
can avoid getting trapped in your usual
media bubble. So, don't wait. Subscribe
now by going to ground.news/charts
or by using the link in the description
or pinned comment. If you use that
address or link, you will get 40% off
unlimited access to their Vantage plan.
Again, that's ground.news/charts.
Okay, let's now return to the three
meanings of the word Israel. The second
way the word Israel is used is in
reference to the Jewish people. Now,
what's the connection between Jews and
ancient Israel? Well, once again, we
have two versions of the story to
consider. The biblical version and the
strictly historical version. This time
the two versions are fairly close, but
there is at least one important
difference. As we've already seen,
according to the Bible, the ancient
kingdom of Israel originally consisted
of 12 tribes, but then one tribe, the
tribe of Judah, split off from the rest
to form its own kingdom called the
kingdom of Judah named after Jacob's son
Judah. This breakaway kingdom outlasted
the other one and whereas the northern
Israelites basically disappear from the
story, Judah does not because even
though it also gets conquered, its
people eventually return to their land
and keep going, albeit now under foreign
rule. By the time we get to the New
Testament, the words Judah and Israel
are being used interchangeably because
Judah is now basically the only tribe
left and therefore it represents Israel
as a whole. Now, from a strictly
historical point of view, things were a
little bit different. You see, there's
some evidence to suggest that Judah and
Israel actually started out as two
separate kingdoms and that it was only
after the destruction of Israel that
Judah started to associate itself with
the name Israel. One of the reasons for
this was that after the northern kingdom
was destroyed, many former Israelites
fled south and joined Judah where they
ended up influencing the culture and
religion there. So, according to this
point of view, the words Israel and
Judah ended up being interchangeable
because in the late Iron Age the two
populations basically combined. However,
take note that by the time of Jesus, the
direct descendants of the ancient
kingdoms of Israel and Judah are mostly
known as Jews after the word Judah. But
even in the New Testament, the term
Israel is still sometimes used. However,
it's now used to refer to a people, not
a state because the ancient Israelite
state is now long gone. This practice
continued after the Romans destroyed
Jerusalem in 70 CE and most Jews spread
throughout Europe. In fact, it continues
to be used all the way up to today even
though there now is once again a state
known as Israel. For example, when the
word Israel is used in most Jewish
prayers, it is not a reverence to the
modern state of Israel, nor is it a
reference to the ancient kingdom of
Israel, nor is it even a reverence to
that area of the world in general,
unless it is preceded by the words land
of. Whenever the word Israel appears on
its own, it's simply a reference to the
Jewish people as a whole, wherever they
may be. So, take note, whereas the first
meaning of the word Israel is directly
tied to a place, the second meaning of
Israel is instead tied to a people. Now,
before I move on, I want to quickly
address whether or not modern Jews are
genealogically connected to the Jews of
ancient times. The simple answer is yes,
they are. Basically, from 70 CE onwards,
the Jews split into three main ethnic
groups. The Mizrahi, who stayed in the
Middle East, the Sephardi, who settled
in Spain, and the Ashkenazi, who settled
in Germany, but were later pushed into
Eastern Europe. The Ashkenazis stand out
because today they look very European.
Well, this is because initially these
Jews intermarried with Italians,
resulting in their genes becoming
approximately 50% Middle Eastern and 50%
European, which is something that has
now been confirmed by multiple DNA
studies. So, modern Ashkenazi Jews are
not fake Jews, or as some people claim,
Khazari converts. They do in fact
descend from the ancient Middle Eastern
Jews. Okay, so that covers the first two
meanings of the word Israel. The third
one, which these days is the most
common, is that it can be used to refer
to the modern country known as the State
of Israel, which was established in 1948
by Zionists.
Zionists are a subset of Jews named
after Mount Zion near Jerusalem, who
wanted to create a Jewish homeland where
Jews could be safe. As I'm sure you
know, Jews were heavily persecuted in
Europe for many centuries with violence
ramping up in the 1800s and eventually
culminating in the Holocaust during
World War II. Now, what a lot of people
don't know is that it wasn't inevitable
that the Zionist state would be
established where it was, nor that it
would be named Israel. Several places
were in fact proposed and even when the
current location was chosen, several
different names were tossed out as
possibilities, including Judea, Zion,
Ever, and even Carmelia, after Mount
Carmel near Haifa. In the end though,
the name Israel was selected. Take note
however, that the citizens of Israel are
known as Israelis, whereas the ancient
people who lived in that land are
referred to as Israelites. Now, in this
video I'm not going to delve into
whether or not I think the state of
Israel should have been created in the
first place, or what is the best
solution for the current situation.
Here, I simply want to drive home the
point that the third meaning of the word
Israel and the second meaning of the
word Israel are not the same. And here's
why that's important. In recent years,
anti-Semitism, meaning hostility towards
Jews, has been on the rise. However, at
the same time, anti-Zionism,
meaning hostility towards the state of
Israel, has also been on the rise. And
these two things are not the same. In my
opinion, just because someone is
critical of the state of Israel, that
doesn't make them an anti-Semite. After
all, there are many Jews, even in Israel
itself, who oppose the actions of the
current government. Conversely though,
if someone is critical of the state of
Israel and thinks that all Jews in all
places are to blame for the actions of
the state of Israel, then that is
anti-Semitism. In both cases, the
problem is conflating Israel, meaning
the Jewish people, with Israel, meaning
the modern state. To sum up, here's a
chart explaining the three meanings. The
first meaning covers Israel as the
ancient kingdom of Israel, which existed
from approximately 930 BCE to 720 BCE,
and individual from this Israel is
referred to as an Israelite. The second
meaning covers Israel as a term for the
Jewish people and has been in use from
at least 720 BCE all the way down to
today. An individual from this Israel is
referred to as a Jew. Finally, the third
meaning covers Israel as the modern
state, which has existed since 1948. An
individual from this Israel is referred
to as an Israeli. Okay, next week I'll
be following up this video with a look
at the word Palestine and the various
different meanings for it. So, be sure
to subscribe and hit the bell so you can
be notified when that comes out. And
don't forget to check out Ground News.
Thanks for watching.